<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Poem in defiance to the Dutch</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28210</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18471285</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206587</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240863752</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2674</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18471285</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206587)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1641:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Poem in defiance to the Dutch</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W.S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes verse entitled "To the king."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:206587:1"/>
            <head>A POEM In DEFIANCE to the DUTCH.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ROb'd of our Rights? and by such water-rats?</l>
               <l>We'l doff their Heads if they wo'nt doff their Hats.</l>
               <l>Affront too <hi>Hogen-Mogen</hi> to endure!</l>
               <l>'Tis time to box these <hi>Butter-Boxes</hi> sure.</l>
               <l>If they the Flags undoughted right deny us?</l>
               <l>Who wo'nt <hi>stricke</hi> to us, must be <hi>stricken</hi> by us.</l>
               <l>A crow of <hi>Boars,</hi> and <hi>Sooterkins,</hi> that know</l>
               <l>Themselves, they to our Blood and Valour owe.</l>
               <l>Did vve for this knock of their <hi>Spannish</hi> Fetters,</l>
               <l>To make 'em able to abuse their betters;</l>
               <l>If at this rate the rave, I think 'tis good,</l>
               <l>Not to omit the <hi>fall,</hi> but let them Blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Rouse then Heroick <hi>Brittains,</hi> 'tis not <hi>words</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>Wounds,</hi> must work with <hi>Leather-Apron Lords.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are <hi>deaf,</hi> to them your meaning break,</l>
               <l>With mouths of <hi>Brass,</hi> that words of Iron speak;</l>
               <l>I hope we shall to purpose the next <hi>hout</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cure 'um, as we did <hi>Opdam</hi> of the Gout.</l>
               <l>And when i'th bottom of the Sea they come,</l>
               <l>They'l have enough of <hi>Mare Liberum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our <hi>Brandisht steel,</hi> tho now they seem so tall,</l>
               <l>Shall make 'em <hi>lower</hi> then <hi>Low-Country</hi> fall.</l>
               <l>But they'l ere long come to themselves you'l see,</l>
               <l>When we in <hi>earnest</hi> are at <hi>Snick-a-snee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When once the <hi>Boars</hi> perceive our Swords are drawn,</l>
               <l>And we converting are those <hi>Boars</hi> to <hi>Brawn.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Methinks the Ruin of their <hi>Belgick</hi> Banners</l>
               <l>Last Fight, almost as ragged as their Manners</l>
               <l>Might have perswaded 'em to better things,</l>
               <l>Then be so sawcy to their betters, KINGS.</l>
               <l>Is it of <hi>Wealth</hi> they are so Proud become?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>JAMES</hi> has a Wain I hope to fetch it home,</l>
               <l>And with it pay <hi>Himself</hi> His just Arrears,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Fishing-Tribute</hi> for this hundred Years.</l>
               <l>That we may say, as all the <hi>Store</hi> comes in,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Dutch,</hi> a lass, have but our <hi>Factors</hi> bin.</l>
               <l>They Fathom <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land,</hi> we when we please,</l>
               <l>Have both the <hi>Indles</hi> brought to our own Seas.</l>
               <l>For <hi>rich,</hi> and <hi>proud,</hi> they bring in Ships by <hi>shoals,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And then we <hi>humble</hi> them to <hi>save</hi> their <hi>Souls.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pox of their <hi>Pictures,</hi> if we had 'em <hi>hear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We'd find 'em <hi>Frames</hi> at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> or else where.</l>
               <l>The next they Draw, be it their <hi>Admirals</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Transpecitated</hi> into <hi>Fynnes</hi> and <hi>Seales;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or, which would do as well, draw if they please,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Opdam,</hi> with the seven sinking Provinces;</l>
               <l>Or draw their <hi>Captains</hi> from the conquering <hi>Mane,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>First beaten <hi>home,</hi> then beaten <hi>back</hi> again;</l>
               <l>And after this so <hi>just,</hi> tho <hi>fatal strife,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Draw their Dead <hi>Boars</hi> again unto the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Lastly, remember, to prevent all <hi>Laughter,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Drawing</hi> goes first, but <hi>Hanging</hi> follows after.</l>
               <l>If then <hi>Lampooning</hi> thus be their undoing,</l>
               <l>Who <hi>pitties</hi> them, that purchase their own ruin?</l>
               <l>Or will hereafter trust their Treachereies,</l>
               <l>Until they leave their <hi>Heads</hi> for Hostages.</l>
               <l>For, as the Proverb has of Women said,—</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beleve 'um not, nay, tho you'd swear there dead.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Dutch</hi> are stubbern, and will yield not frute,</l>
               <l>Till, like the <hi>Wallnut-Tree</hi> ye beat 'um to't.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="section">
               <head>To the KING.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I See an <hi>Age,</hi> when after some few years,</l>
                  <l>And Revolutions of the slow pac'd <hi>Sphears;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>These days shall be 'bove others far esteem'd,</l>
                  <l>And like the Worlds great Conquerers be deem'd.</l>
                  <l>The Names of <hi>Coesar,</hi> and feign'd <hi>Paladine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Grav'n in <hi>Times</hi> surley brows, in wrinkled-Time,</l>
                  <l>Shall by this Princes Name be past as far,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Meteors</hi> are by the <hi>Idalian</hi> Star:</l>
                  <l>For to Great <hi>Brittains</hi> Isle thou shalt restore</l>
                  <l>Her <hi>Mare Clausum;</hi> Gaurd her Pearly Shore.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Lyons Passant</hi> of <hi>Dutch</hi> Bands shalt free,</l>
                  <l>To the true owner of the <hi>Lilles</hi> three.</l>
                  <l>The Seas shall shrink, shake shall the spacious Earth,</l>
                  <l>And tremble in her Chamber, like pale Death.</l>
                  <l>Thy thundring Cannons shall proclaim to all</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Great Brittain</hi>'s Glory, and proud <hi>Hollands</hi> fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Run on brave Prince thy course in Glory's way,</l>
                  <l>The end the life, the evening <hi>Crowns</hi> the day.</l>
                  <l>Reap Worth on Worth, and strongly sore above</l>
                  <l>Those heights which made the World <hi>Thee</hi> first to Love.</l>
                  <l>Surmount thy Self, and make thy Actions past</l>
                  <l>Be but as <hi>Gleams</hi> or <hi>Lightnings</hi> of thy last.</l>
                  <l>Let them exceed those of Thy <hi>younger</hi> time;</l>
                  <l>As far as <hi>Autumn</hi> doth the Flowry-prime;</l>
                  <l>So ever Gold and Bays Thy Brow adorn;</l>
                  <l>So never <hi>Time</hi> may see Thy <hi>Rase</hi> out worn.</l>
                  <l>So of Thine own still may'st Thou be desir'd;</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Holland</hi> feard, and by the <hi>World</hi> Admir'd;</l>
                  <l>Till Thy great Deeds all former deeds surmount:</l>
                  <l>Thou'st quel'd the <hi>Nimrods</hi> of our <hi>Hellespont.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So may His high Exploits at last make even</l>
                  <l>With Earth His <hi>Honour,</hi> Glory with the Heav'n.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. S.</hi> in the Year 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>